<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
      <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                  <titleStmt>
                        <title>Coopers Hill (1655)</title>
                        <author>John Denham</author>
                        <respStmt>
                              <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                              <name>Tiago Sousa Garcia</name>
                        </respStmt>
                  </titleStmt>
                  <publicationStmt>
                        <p>Coopers Hill SDE</p>
                  </publicationStmt>
                  <sourceDesc>
                        <bibl>
                              <title>Coopers Hill</title>
                              <author>John Denham</author>
                              <date>1655</date>
                        </bibl>
                  </sourceDesc>
            </fileDesc>
      </teiHeader>
      <text>
            <front>
                  <div type="title">
                        <pb xml:id="A1r"
                              facs="http://gateway.proquest.com/openurl?ctx_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;res_id=xri:eebo&amp;rft_id=xri:eebo:image:46676"/>
                        <head type="title" rend="center">COOPERS HILL.</head>
                        <head type="subtitle" rend="center">Written in the yeare 1640.</head>
                        <head type="addInformation" rend="italic">Now printed from a perfect Copy;
                              And<lb/>A Corrected Impression</head>
                  </div>
                  <div type="Author">
                        <p>By <name>John Denham</name>, Esq.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="imprint">
                        <p rend="center"><placeName rend="italic">London</placeName><lb/>Printed for
                                    <name rend="italic">Humphrey Moseley</name>, and are to be sold
                              at his shop at the Signe of the Princes Arms in St <hi rend="italic"
                                    >Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1655.</p>
                  </div>
            </front>
            <body>
                  <div type="poem">
                        <pb xml:id="B1r"
                              facs="http://gateway.proquest.com/openurl?ctx_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;res_id=xri:eebo&amp;rft_id=xri:eebo:image:46676:3"/>
                        <head type="title">Coopers Hill.<note type="gloss"><ref
                                          target="https://goo.gl/maps/YmAwtWgySQz8oFQF6">A small
                                          hill (c. 220 ft) in Egham, near Windsor</ref>. Coopers
                                    Hill overlooks Runnymeade, Windsor and the River Thames.
                                    Although relatively close to central London and across the river
                                    from Heathrow Airport, it is unlikely (though not entirely
                                    impossible) that any observer could actually spot the spire of
                                    St. Paul's Cathedral, as Denham claims.</note> [1655]</head>
                        <div type="verse">
                              <l><hi rend="initial">I</hi>F there be Poets, which did never
                                    dreame</l>
                              <l>Upon Parnassus,<note type="gloss">Mount Parnassus, in Greece, the
                                          home of the Muses.</note> nor did tast the streame</l>
                              <l>Of Helicon,<note type="gloss">Mount Helicon, in Greece, where two
                                          springs sacred to the Muses were located, the Aganippe and
                                          the Hippocrene. The waters of the Hippocrene were supposed
                                          to bring poetic inspiration.</note> we justly may
                                    suppose,</l>
                              <l>Those made not Poets, but the Poets those.</l>
                              <l>And as Courts make not Kings, but Kings the Court,<note
                                          type="gloss">Possibly a topical allusion to the <ref
                                                target="https://www.parliament.uk/about/living-heritage/evolutionofparliament/houseoflords/judicialrole/overview/highcourtparliament/"
                                                >High Court of Parliament</ref>, though more likely
                                          simply alluding to the royal court, i.e., the extended
                                          household of the monarch.</note></l>
                              <l>So where the Muses and their traine resort,</l>
                              <l>Parnassus stands; if I can be to thee</l>
                              <l>A Poet, thou Parnassus art to mee.</l>
                              <l>Nor wonder, if (advantag'd in my flight,</l>
                              <l>By taking wing from thy auspicious height)</l>
                              <l>Through untrac't waies, and ayrie paths I flye,</l>
                              <l>More boundlesse in my Fancy, then my eye:</l>
                              <l>My eye, which swift as thought contracts the space</l>
                              <l>That lyes between, and first salutes the place</l>
                              <l>Crown'd with that sacred pile, so vast, so high,</l>
                              <l>That whether 'tis a part of Earth, or sky,</l>
                              <pb xml:id="B1v"
                                    facs="http://gateway.proquest.com/openurl?ctx_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;res_id=xri:eebo&amp;rft_id=xri:eebo:image:46676:4"/>
                              <l>Uncertaine seemes, and may be thought a proud</l>
                              <l>Aspiring mountain, or a falling cloud,</l>
                              <l>Pauls,<note type="gloss"><ref
                                                target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Old_St_Paul%27s_Cathedral#/media/File:StPaul'sCross.jpg"
                                                >Old St. Paul's Cathedral</ref>, that burned down in
                                          the Great Fire of London (1666).</note> the late theme of
                                    such a Muse whose flight <note type="side-note" place="margin"
                                          rend="italic">Master Waler<note type="gloss">Cf. Edmund
                                                Waller's '<ref
                                                  target="https://rpo.library.utoronto.ca/poems/upon-his-majesty%E2%80%99s-repairing-paul%E2%80%99s"
                                                  >Upon His Majesties repairing of
                                                Pauls</ref>'.</note></note></l>
                              <l>Has bravely reach't and soar'd above thy height:</l>
                              <l>Now shalt thou stand, though sword, or time,or fire,</l>
                              <l>Or zeale<note type="gloss">Specifically Puritan zeal, that rebelled
                                          against the trappings of old religion.</note> more fierce
                                    then they, thy fall conspire,</l>
                              <l>Secure, whilst thee the best of Poets sings,</l>
                              <l>Preserv'd from ruine by the best of Kings.<note type="gloss"><ref
                                                target="https://doi.org/10.1093/ref:odnb/5143"
                                                >Charles I</ref>.</note></l>
                              <l>Vunder his proud survay the Citty lyes,</l>
                              <l>And like a mist beneath a hill doth rise;</l>
                              <l>Whose state and wealth, the busines and the crowd,</l>
                              <l>Seems at this distance but a darker cloud:</l>
                              <l>And is to him, who rightly things esteems,</l>
                              <l>No other in effect then what it seems:</l>
                              <l>Where with like hast, through several waies, they run,</l>
                              <l>Some to undo, and some to be undone;</l>
                              <l>While luxury, and wealth, like war and peace,</l>
                              <l>Are each the others ruine, and increase;</l>
                              <l>As Rivers lost in Seas some secret veine</l>
                              <l>Thence reconveighs, there to be lost again.</l>
                              <pb xml:id="B2r"
                                    facs="http://gateway.proquest.com/openurl?ctx_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;res_id=xri:eebo&amp;rft_id=xri:eebo:image:46676:4"/>
                              <l>Oh happinesse of sweet retir'd content!</l>
                              <l>To be at once secure,and innocent.</l>
                              <l><hi rend="italic">Windsor</hi> the next (where <hi rend="italic"
                                          >Mars</hi> with <hi rend="italic">Venus</hi> dwells,<note
                                          type="gloss">Partly symbols of strength and beauty, as
                                          Windsor castle, partly symbols for Charles I and <ref
                                                target="https://doi.org/10.1093/ref:odnb/12947"
                                                >Henrietta Maria</ref>, his queen consort. It was
                                          common to represent reigning monarchs and their consorts
                                          as Mars and Venus in Renaissance painting.</note>
                                    <note type="side-note" place="margin" rend="italic"
                                          >Windsor.</note></l>
                              <l>Beauty with strength) above the valley swells</l>
                              <l>Into my eye, and doth it self present</l>
                              <l>With such an easie and unforc't ascent,</l>
                              <l>That no stupendious precipice denyes</l>
                              <l>Accesse, no horror turnes away our eyes:</l>
                              <l>But such a Rise, as doth at once invite</l>
                              <l>A pleasure, and a reverence from the sight.</l>
                              <l>Thy mighty Masters Embleme,<note type="gloss">The master is Charles
                                          I, the castle his emblem.</note> in whose face</l>
                              <l>Sate meeknesse, heightned with Majestick Grace.</l>
                              <l>Such seems thy gentle height, made onely proud</l>
                              <l>To be the basis of that pompous load,</l>
                              <l>Then which, a Nobler weight not Mountain Bears,</l>
                              <l>But <hi rend="italic">Atlas</hi><note type="gloss">In Greek
                                          mythology Atlas was a Titan condenmned to hold the heavens
                                          for eternity.</note> only that supports the Sphears.</l>
                              <l>When Natures hand this ground did thus advance,</l>
                              <l>'Twas guided by a wiser power then Chance;</l>
                              <l>Mark't out for such a use, as if 'twere meant</l>
                              <l>T'invite the builder, and his choice prevent.</l>
                              <pb xml:id="B2v"
                                    facs="http://gateway.proquest.com/openurl?ctx_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;res_id=xri:eebo&amp;rft_id=xri:eebo:image:46676:5"/>
                              <l>Nor can we call it choice, when what we chuse,</l>
                              <l>Folly, or blindnes only could refuse.</l>
                              <l>A Crown of such Majestick towrs doth Grace</l>
                              <l>The Gods great Mother,<note type="gloss">The goddess Cybele,
                                          Phrygian mother of the gods, later adopted into Greek
                                          mythology.</note> when her heavenly race</l>
                              <l>Doe homage to her, yet she cannot boast</l>
                              <l>Amongst that numerous, and Celestiall hoast,</l>
                              <l>More <hi rend="italic">Hero's</hi> than can <hi rend="italic"
                                          >VVindsor</hi>, nor doth Fames</l>
                              <l>Immortall booke record more noble names.</l>
                              <l>Not to look back so far, to whom this Ile</l>
                              <l>Owes the first Glory so brave a pile,</l>
                              <l>Whether to <hi rend="italic">Caesar,</hi><note type="gloss">Julius
                                          Caesar, who first invaded Britain.</note>
                                    <hi rend="italic">Albanact,</hi><note type="gloss">Albanactus,
                                          mythical founding king of the kingdom of Albania, roughly
                                          modern-day Scotland</note> or <hi rend="italic"
                                          >Brute,</hi><note type="gloss">Brutus of Troy, the
                                          legendary founder and first king of Britain.</note></l>
                              <l>The Brittish <hi rend="italic">Arthur,</hi><note type="gloss">King
                                          Arthur, legendary Celtic king who fought against the Saxon
                                          invasion of Britain; central character in the medieval
                                          romances that make up the Matter of Britain.</note> or the
                                    Danish <hi rend="italic">Knute,</hi><note type="gloss">King
                                          Canute, Danish king of Denmark, England and Norway (the
                                          North Sea Empire). Famously portrayed in an anecdote in
                                          which he demonstrates the futility of 'trying to stop the
                                          tide.'</note></l>
                              <l>(Though this of old no lesse contest did move,</l>
                              <l>Then when for <hi rend="italic">Homers</hi> birth seven Cities
                                          strove<note type="gloss">Homer's birthplace (if one is to
                                          accept that Homer ever existed as a single person) is
                                          uncertain and, from antiquity, seven cities have claimed
                                          to be Homer's birthplace.</note>)</l>
                              <l>(Like him in birth, thou should'st be like in Fame,</l>
                              <l>As thine his fate, if mine had been his Flame)</l>
                              <l>But whosoere it was, Nature design'd</l>
                              <l>First a brave place, and then as brave a minde.</l>
                              <l>Not to recount those severall Kings, to whom</l>
                              <l>It gave a Cradle, or to whom a Tombe,</l>
                              <pb xml:id="B3r"
                                    facs="http://gateway.proquest.com/openurl?ctx_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;res_id=xri:eebo&amp;rft_id=xri:eebo:image:46676:5"/>
                              <l>But thee (great <hi rend="italic">Edward</hi>) and thy greater
                                          sonne,<note type="gloss"><ref
                                                target="https://doi.org/10.1093/ref:odnb/8523"
                                                >Edward the Black Prince</ref> had a famous victory
                                          at Poitiers in 1356 in which he captured his father's
                                          rival, King John of France.</note>
                                    <note type="side-note" place="margin" rend="italic">Edward the
                                          3. and the black prince.</note></l>
                              <l>(The lillies <note type="gloss">The fleurs-de-lis, that is, the
                                          French crown. <ref
                                                target="https://doi.org/10.1093/ref:odnb/8519"
                                                >Edward III</ref> was the first English king to
                                          claim the French throne.</note> which his Father wore, he
                                    wonne)</l>
                              <l>And thy <hi rend="italic">Bellona,</hi><note type="gloss">Roman
                                          goddess of war</note> who the Consort came</l>
                              <l>Not onely to thy bed, but to thy Fame, <note type="side-note"
                                          place="margin" rend="italic">Queene Philip.<note
                                                type="gloss">Phillipa of Hainault, Queen consort of
                                                Edward III.</note></note></l>
                              <l>She to thy Triumph led one Captive King, <note type="side-note"
                                          place="margin" rend="italic">The Kings of France &amp;
                                          Scotland.</note></l>
                              <l>And brought that sonne, which did the second bring.<note
                                          type="gloss">At one time, Edward III held captive the
                                          kings of France and Scotland simultaneously.</note></l>
                              <l>Then didst thou found that Order <note type="gloss"><ref
                                                target="https://www.stgeorges-windsor.org/about-st-georges/history/the-order-of-the-garter/"
                                                >The Order of the Garter</ref>, founded by Edward
                                          III in 1349.</note>(whither love,</l>
                              <l>Or victory thy Royall thoughts did move)</l>
                              <l>Each was a noble cause, and nothing lesse,</l>
                              <l>Then the designe, has been the great successe:</l>
                              <l>Which forraigne Kings, and Emperors esteeme</l>
                              <l>The second Honour to their Diadem.<note type="gloss">Foreign kings
                                          and princes, particularly those who were connected to the
                                          English royal family through marriage or alliance, were
                                          often made knights of the Garter.</note></l>
                              <l>Had thy great destiny but given thee skill,</l>
                              <l>To know as well, as power to act her will,</l>
                              <l>That from those Kings, who then thy captives were,</l>
                              <l>In after-times should spring a Royall paire,<note type="gloss"
                                          >Charles I, descendent of the Scottish Stuarts, and
                                          Henrietta Maria, daughter of Henri IV of
                                    France.</note></l>
                              <l>Who should possesse all that thy mighty power,</l>
                              <l>Or thy desires more mighty, did devoure;</l>
                              <l>To whom their better Fate reserves what ere</l>
                              <l>The Victor hopes for, or the Vanquisht feare;</l>
                              <pb xml:id="B3v"
                                    facs="http://gateway.proquest.com/openurl?ctx_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;res_id=xri:eebo&amp;rft_id=xri:eebo:image:46676:6"/>
                              <l>That blood, which thou and thy great Grandsire shed,</l>
                              <l>And all that since these sister Nations bled,</l>
                              <l>Had bin unspilt, had happy <hi rend="italic">Edward</hi> known</l>
                              <l>That all the blood he spilt, had been his own.</l>
                              <l>When he that Patron<note type="gloss">St. George is the Patron
                                          Saint of the Order.</note> chose, in whom are joyn'd</l>
                              <l>Souldier and Martyr, and his arms confin'd</l>
                              <l>Within the Azure Circle, he did seem</l>
                              <l>But to foretel, and prophecie of him,</l>
                              <l>Who to his Realms that Azure round hath joyn'd,</l>
                              <l>Which Nature for their bound at first design'd.</l>
                              <l>That bound, which to the Worlds extreamest ends,</l>
                              <l>Endlesse it selfe, its liquid arms extends;</l>
                              <l>He, who not needs that Embleme which we paint,</l>
                              <l>But is himself the Souldier and the Saint.<note type="gloss"
                                          >Charles I. Charles shown himself to be a soldier during
                                          the civil war and became a royalist martyr (and later a
                                          Saint in the Anglican faith), at his execution in
                                          1649.</note></l>
                              <l>Here should my wonder dwell, and here my praise,</l>
                              <l>But my fixt thoughts my wandring eye betrays,</l>
                              <l>Viewing a neighboring hill,<note type="gloss">St. Anne's Hill in
                                          Chertsey.</note> whose top of late</l>
                              <l>A Chappel crown'd, till in the Common Fate,</l>
                              <l>The adjoyning Abby<note type="gloss"><ref
                                                target="https://historicengland.org.uk/listing/the-list/list-entry/1008524"
                                                >Chertsey Abbey</ref>.</note> fell:<note
                                          type="gloss">The dissolution of the monasteries, ordered
                                          by Henry VIII.</note> (may no such storme</l>
                              <l>Fall on our times, where ruine must reform.)</l>
                              <pb xml:id="B4r"
                                    facs="http://gateway.proquest.com/openurl?ctx_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;res_id=xri:eebo&amp;rft_id=xri:eebo:image:46676:6"/>
                              <l>Tell me (my Muse) what monstrous dire Offence,</l>
                              <l>What crime could any Christian incense</l>
                              <l>To such a rage? was't Luxury? or lust?</l>
                              <l>Was he so temperate, so chast, so just?</l>
                              <l>Were these their crimes? they were his own much more:</l>
                              <l>But wealth is Crime enough to him that's poor,</l>
                              <l>Who having spent the Treasures of his Crown,</l>
                              <l>Condemns their Luxury to feed his own.</l>
                              <l>And yet this Act, to varnish o're the shame</l>
                              <l>Of sacriledge, must bear devotions name.</l>
                              <l>No Crime so bold, but would be understood</l>
                              <l>A reall, or at least a seeming good.</l>
                              <l>Who fears not to do ill, yet fears the Name,</l>
                              <l>And free from Conscience, is a slave to Fame.</l>
                              <l>Thus he the Church at once protects, and spoyles:</l>
                              <l>But Princes swords are sharper then their styles.</l>
                              <l>And thus to th'ages past he makes amends,</l>
                              <l>Their Charity destroyes, their Faith defends.<note type="gloss"
                                          >Allusion to Henry's title as 'Defender of the
                                          Faith.'</note></l>
                              <l>Then did Religion in a lazie Cell ,</l>
                              <l>In emptie, airie contemplations dwell;</l>
                              <pb xml:id="B4v"
                                    facs="http://gateway.proquest.com/openurl?ctx_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;res_id=xri:eebo&amp;rft_id=xri:eebo:image:46676:7"/>
                              <l>And like the block, unmoved lay: but ours,</l>
                              <l>As much too active, like the storke devours.</l>
                              <l>Is there no temperate Region can be knowne,</l>
                              <l>Betwixt their Frigid, and our Torrid Zone?</l>
                              <l>Could we not wake from that Lethargicke Dreame,</l>
                              <l>But to be restlesse in a worse extreame?</l>
                              <l>And for that Lethargy was there no cure,</l>
                              <l>But to be cast into a Calenture?<note type="gloss">Feverish
                                          delirium.</note></l>
                              <l>Can knowledge have no bound, but must advance</l>
                              <l>So farre, to make us wish for ignorance?</l>
                              <l>And rather in the darke to grope our way,</l>
                              <l>Then led by a false guide to erre by day?</l>
                              <l>Who sees these dismall heaps, but would demand,</l>
                              <l>What barbarous Invader sackt the land?</l>
                              <l>But when he heares, no Goth,<note type="gloss">The Goths were a
                                          germanic people that played an important part in the fall
                                          of the Western Roman Empire at the start of the medieval
                                          period.</note> no Turk<note type="gloss">The Ottoman
                                          empire was the principal opponent of the Christian Kings
                                          and Empires in the early modern period.</note> did
                                    bring</l>
                              <l>This desolation, but a Christian King;</l>
                              <l>When nothing, but the Name of Zeale, appeares</l>
                              <l>'Twixt our best actions and the worst of theirs,</l>
                              <l>What does he think our Sacriledge would spare,</l>
                              <l>When such th'effects of our devotions are?</l>
                              <pb xml:id="C1r"
                                    facs="http://gateway.proquest.com/openurl?ctx_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;res_id=xri:eebo&amp;rft_id=xri:eebo:image:46676:7"/>
                              <l>Parting from thence 'twixt anger, shame, and feare,</l>
                              <l>Those for what's past, and this for what's too neare:</l>
                              <l>My eye descending from the Hill, survaies</l>
                              <l>Where <hi rend="italic">Thames</hi> amongst the wanton vallies
                                    strayes.</l>
                              <l><hi rend="italic">Thames</hi>, the most lov'd of all the Oceans
                                    sonnes, <note type="side-note" place="margin" rend="italic"
                                          >Thames.</note></l>
                              <l>By his old Sire, to his imbraces runnes,</l>
                              <l>Hasting to pay his tribute to the Sea,</l>
                              <l>Like mortall life to meet Eternity.</l>
                              <l>Though with those streames he no resemblance hold,</l>
                              <l>Whose foame is Amber, and their Gravell Gold;</l>
                              <l>His genuine, and lesse guilty wealth t'explore,</l>
                              <l>Search not his bottom, but survey his shore;</l>
                              <l>Ore which he kindly spreads his spacious wing,</l>
                              <l>And hatches plenty for th'ensuing Spring.</l>
                              <l>Nor then destroyes it with too fond a stay,</l>
                              <l>Like Mothers which their Infats overlay.</l>
                              <l>Nor with a suddain and impetuous wave,</l>
                              <l>Like profuse Kings, resumes the wealth he gave.</l>
                              <l>No unexpected inundations spoyle</l>
                              <l>The mowers hopes, nor mock the plowmans toyle:</l>
                              <pb xml:id="C1v"
                                    facs="http://gateway.proquest.com/openurl?ctx_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;res_id=xri:eebo&amp;rft_id=xri:eebo:image:46676:8"/>
                              <l>But Godlike his unwearied Bounty flows;</l>
                              <l>First loves to do, then loves the Good he does.</l>
                              <l>Nor are his Blessings to his banks confin'd,</l>
                              <l>But free, and common, as the Sea or Wind;</l>
                              <l>When he to boast, or to disperse his stores</l>
                              <l>Full of the tributes of his gratefull shores,</l>
                              <l>Visits the World, and in his flying towers</l>
                              <l>Brings home to us, and makes both Indies ours;<note type="gloss"
                                          >The 'west indies' (America) and India proper.</note></l>
                              <l>Finds wealth where 'tis, bestows it where it wants,</l>
                              <l>Citties in deserts, woods in Cities plants.</l>
                              <l>So that to us no thing, no place is strange,</l>
                              <l>While his fayre bosome is the worlds exchange.<note type="gloss">As
                                          in 'Royal Exchange,' i.e., a place of trade and
                                          wealth.</note></l>
                              <l>O could I flow like thee, and make thy streame</l>
                              <l>My great example, as it is my theme!</l>
                              <l>Though deep, yet cleare, though Gentle, yet not dull,</l>
                              <l>Strong without rage, without 'ore-flowing full.</l>
                              <l>Here Nature, whether more intent to please <note type="side-note"
                                          place="margin" rend="italic">The Forrest.</note></l>
                              <l>Us, or her selfe, with strange varieties,</l>
                              <l>(For things of wonder give no lesse delight</l>
                              <l>To the wise Maker's, then beholder's sight.</l>
                              <pb xml:id="C2r"
                                    facs="http://gateway.proquest.com/openurl?ctx_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;res_id=xri:eebo&amp;rft_id=xri:eebo:image:46676:8"/>
                              <l>Though these delights from severall causes move,</l>
                              <l>For so our children, thus our friends we love)</l>
                              <l>Wisely she knew, the harmony of things,</l>
                              <l>As well as that of sounds, from discords springs.</l>
                              <l>Such was the discord, which did first disperse</l>
                              <l>Forme, order, beauty through the Universe;</l>
                              <l>While drynesse moysture, coldnesse heat resists,<note type="gloss"
                                          >Dryness, Moisture, Coldness and Heat are the four 'roots'
                                          of all things according to Empedocles. The four elements
                                          (fire, water, air, and earth) are formed of pairs of these
                                          root qualities.</note></l>
                              <l>All that we have, and that we are, subsists.</l>
                              <l>While the steepe horrid roughnesse of the Wood</l>
                              <l>Strives with the gentle calmenesse of the flood.</l>
                              <l>Such huge extreames when Nature doth unite,</l>
                              <l>Wonder from thence results, from thence delight.</l>
                              <l>The streame is so transparent, pure, and cleare,</l>
                              <l>That had the selfe-enamour'd youth gaz'd here, <note
                                          type="side-note" place="margin" rend="italic"
                                                >Narcissus.<note type="gloss">In Greek mythology,
                                                Narcissus was famed for his beauty and his disdain
                                                for those who loved him. In Ovid's <title><ref
                                                  target="http://classics.mit.edu/Ovid/metam.3.third.html"
                                                  >Metamorphoses</ref></title>, Echo, a nymph, falls
                                                in love with him. Narcissus shuns her love and for
                                                that is punished by Aphrodite, who makes him fall in
                                                love with his own reflection and transforms him into
                                                a flower.</note></note></l>
                              <l>So fatally deceiv'd he had not been,</l>
                              <l>While he the bottome, not his face had seene.</l>
                              <l>But his proud head the ayery Mountaine hides</l>
                              <l>Among the Clouds; his shoulders, and his sides</l>
                              <l>A shady mantle cloaths; his curled brows</l>
                              <l>Frowne on the Gentle streame, which calmly flows,</l>
                              <pb xml:id="C2v"
                                    facs="http://gateway.proquest.com/openurl?ctx_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;res_id=xri:eebo&amp;rft_id=xri:eebo:image:46676:9"/>
                              <l>While winds and stormes his lofty forhead beat:</l>
                              <l>The common fate of all that's high, or great.</l>
                              <l>Low at his foot a spacious plaine is plac't,</l>
                              <l>Between the mountaine and the streame imbrac't:</l>
                              <l>Which shade and shelter from the Hill derives,</l>
                              <l>While the kind river wealth and beauty gives;</l>
                              <l>And in the mixture of all these appeares</l>
                              <l>Variety, which all the rest indears.</l>
                              <l>This scene had some bold Greek, or Brittish Bard<note type="gloss"
                                          >There seems to be no clear referent for these
                                          bards.</note></l>
                              <l>Beheld of old, what stories had we heard,</l>
                              <l>Of Faries, Satyrs, and the Nymphs their Dames,</l>
                              <l>Their feasts, their revells, and their amorous flames!</l>
                              <l>'Tis still the same, although their ayery shape</l>
                              <l>All but a quick Poetick sight escape.</l>
                              <l>There Faunus<note type="gloss">Roman god of animals.</note> and
                                          Sylvanus<note type="gloss">Roman god of woodlands.</note>
                                    keepe their Courts,</l>
                              <l>And thither all the horned hoast resorts,</l>
                              <l>To graze the rancker meade, that noble heard,</l>
                              <l>On whose sublime and shady fronts is reard</l>
                              <l>Natures great Masterpeece; to shew how soone</l>
                              <l>Great things are made, but sooner are undone.</l>
                              <pb xml:id="C3r"
                                    facs="http://gateway.proquest.com/openurl?ctx_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;res_id=xri:eebo&amp;rft_id=xri:eebo:image:46676:9"/>
                              <l>Here have I seene the King,<note type="gloss">In 1655 when this
                                          poem is published there is no king: Charles I had been
                                          executed in 1649 and his son, the future <ref
                                                target="https://doi.org/10.1093/ref:odnb/5144"
                                                >Charles II</ref>, is in exile. Britain is a
                                          commonwealth, rulled by a council of state and a Lord
                                          Protector, <ref
                                                target="https://doi.org/10.1093/ref:odnb/6765"
                                                >Oliver Cromwell</ref>.</note> when great
                                    affaires</l>
                              <l>Give leave to slacken, and unbend his cares,</l>
                              <l>Attended to the Chase by all the flower</l>
                              <l>Of youth, whose hopes a Nobler prey devoure:</l>
                              <l>Pleasure with Praise, and danger, they would buy,</l>
                              <l>And with a foe that would not only fly.</l>
                              <l>The stagg<note type="gloss">Stags were amongst the most prized and
                                          most noble game.</note> now conscious of his fatall
                                    Growth,</l>
                              <l>At once indulgent to his feare and sloth,</l>
                              <l>To some darke covert his retreat had made,</l>
                              <l>Where nor mans eye, nor heavens should invade</l>
                              <l>His soft repose; when th'unexpected sound</l>
                              <l>Of doggs, and men, his wakefull eare doth wound.</l>
                              <l>Rouz'd with the noyse, he scarse believes his eare,</l>
                              <l>Willing to think th'illusions of his feare</l>
                              <l>Had given this false Alar'm, but straight his view</l>
                              <l>Confirmes, that more than all he feares is true.</l>
                              <l>Betray'd in all his strengths, the wood beset,</l>
                              <l>All instruments, all Arts of ruine met;</l>
                              <l>He calls to mind his strength, and then his speed,</l>
                              <l>His winged heeles, and then his armed head;</l>
                              <pb xml:id="C3v"
                                    facs="http://gateway.proquest.com/openurl?ctx_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;res_id=xri:eebo&amp;rft_id=xri:eebo:image:46676:10"/>
                              <l>With these t'avoyd, with that his Fate to meet:</l>
                              <l>But feare prevails, and bids him trust his feet.</l>
                              <l>So fast he flyes, that his reviewing eye</l>
                              <l>Has lost the chasers, their Nobler sense</l>
                              <l>Their disproportion'd speed does recompense.</l>
                              <l>Then curses his conspiring feet, whose scent</l>
                              <l>Betrayes that safety which their swiftnesse lent.</l>
                              <l>Then tryes his friends, among the baser heard,</l>
                              <l>Where he so lately was obey'd, and fear'd,</l>
                              <l>His safety seeks: the heard, unkindly wise,<note type="gloss">Wise
                                          beyond their kind (i.e., against their nature), or
                                          possibly wise in an unkind manner.</note></l>
                              <l>Or chases him from thence, or from him flyes.</l>
                              <l>Like a declining Statesman, left forlorne</l>
                              <l>To his friends pitty, and pursuers scorne,</l>
                              <l>With shame remembers, while himsefe was one</l>
                              <l>Of the same heard, himselfe the same had done.</l>
                              <l>Thence to the coverts, and the conscious Groves,</l>
                              <l>The scenes of his past triumphs, and his loves;</l>
                              <l>Sadly surveying where he rang'd alone</l>
                              <l>Prince of the soyle, and all the heard his owne;</l>
                              <pb xml:id="C4r"
                                    facs="http://gateway.proquest.com/openurl?ctx_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;res_id=xri:eebo&amp;rft_id=xri:eebo:image:46676:10"/>
                              <l>And like a bold Knight Errant did proclaime</l>
                              <l>Combat to all, and bore away the Dame;</l>
                              <l>And taught the woods to eccho to the streame</l>
                              <l>His dreadfull challenge, and his clashing beame.</l>
                              <l>Yet faintly now declines the fatall strife;</l>
                              <l>So much his love was dearer then his life.</l>
                              <l>Now every lease, and every moving breath</l>
                              <l>Presents a foe, and every foe a death.</l>
                              <l>Wearied, forsaken, and pursu'd, at last</l>
                              <l>All safety in despaire of safety plac'd,</l>
                              <l>Courage he thence resumes, resolv'd to beare</l>
                              <l>All their assaults, since 'tis in vaine to feare.</l>
                              <l>And now too late he wishes for the fight</l>
                              <l>That strength he wasted in Ignoble flight:</l>
                              <l>But when he sees the eager chase renew'd,</l>
                              <l>Himselfe by doggs, the doggs by men pursu'd:</l>
                              <l>He straight revokes his bold resolve, and more</l>
                              <l>Repents his courage, then his feare before;</l>
                              <l>Finds that uncertaine waies unsafest are,</l>
                              <l>And Doubt a greater mischief then Despaire.</l>
                              <pb xml:id="C4v"
                                    facs="http://gateway.proquest.com/openurl?ctx_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;res_id=xri:eebo&amp;rft_id=xri:eebo:image:46676:11"/>
                              <l>Then to the streame, when neither friends, nor force,</l>
                              <l>Nor speed, nor Art availe, he shapes his course;</l>
                              <l>Thinks not their rage so desperate t' assay,</l>
                              <l>An Element, more mercilesse then they.</l>
                              <l>But feareless they pursue, nor can the flood</l>
                              <l>Quench their dire thirst; alas, they thirst for blood.</l>
                              <l>So towards a Ship the oarefin'd Gallyes ply,</l>
                              <l>Which wanting Sea to ride, or wind to fly,</l>
                              <l>Stands but to fall reveng'd on those that dare</l>
                              <l>Tempt the last fury of extreame despayre.</l>
                              <l>So fares the Stagg among th'inraged hounds,</l>
                              <l>Repells their force, and wounds returns for wounds.</l>
                              <l>And as a Hero, whom his baser foes</l>
                              <l>In troops surround, now these assailes, now those,</l>
                              <l>Though prodigall of life, disdaines to dy</l>
                              <l>By common hands; but if he can descry</l>
                              <l>Some nobler foes approach, to him he calls,</l>
                              <l>And beggs his Fate, and then contented falls.</l>
                              <l>So when the King a mortall shaft lets fly</l>
                              <l>From his unerring hand, then glad to dy,</l>
                              <pb xml:id="D1r"
                                    facs="http://gateway.proquest.com/openurl?ctx_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;res_id=xri:eebo&amp;rft_id=xri:eebo:image:46676:11"/>
                              <l>Proud of the wound, to it resigns his blood,</l>
                              <l>And staines the Christall with a Purple<note type="gloss">The
                                          colour purple has long been associated with royalty.
                                          During the early modern period, <ref
                                                target="http://elizabethan.org/sumptuary/">sumptuory
                                                laws</ref> forbade the use of purple by anyone but
                                          the highest members of the aristocracy (the monarch, their
                                          immediate family, and Dukes).</note> flood.</l>
                              <l>This a more Innocent, and happy chase,</l>
                              <l>Then when of old, but in the selfe-same place, <note
                                          type="side-note" place="margin" rend="italic">Runny Mead
                                          where the great Charter<note type="gloss"><ref
                                                  target="https://www.bl.uk/magna-carta/articles/magna-carta-an-introduction"
                                                  >Magna Carta</ref>, signed at Runny Meade.</note>
                                          was first sealed.</note></l>
                              <l>Faire liberty pursu'd, and meant a Prey</l>
                              <l>To lawless power, here turn'd, and stood at bay.</l>
                              <l>When in that remedy all hope was plac't</l>
                              <l>Which was, or should have been at least, the last.</l>
                              <l>Here was that Charter seal'd, wherein the Crowne <note
                                          type="side-note" place="margin" rend="italic">Magna
                                          Carta.</note></l>
                              <l>All markes of Arbitrary power layes downe:</l>
                              <l>Tyrant and slave, those names of hate and feare,</l>
                              <l>The happier stile of King and Subject beare:</l>
                              <l>Happy, when both to the same Center move,</l>
                              <l>When Kings give liberty, and Subjects love.</l>
                              <l>Therefore not long in force this Charter stood;</l>
                              <l>Wanting that seale, it must be seal'd in blood.</l>
                              <l>The Subjects arm'd, the more their Princes gave,</l>
                              <l>Th'advantage only took more to crave:</l>
                              <l>Till Kings by giving, give themselves away,</l>
                              <l>And even that power, that should deny, betray.</l>
                              <pb xml:id="D1v"
                                    facs="http://gateway.proquest.com/openurl?ctx_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;res_id=xri:eebo&amp;rft_id=xri:eebo:image:46676:12"/>
                              <l>"Who gives constraiu'd, but his owne feare reviles,</l>
                              <l>"Not thank't, but scorn'd; nor are they gifts, but spoyles.</l>
                              <l>Thus Kings, by grasping more then they could, hold,</l>
                              <l>First made their Subjects by oppression bold:</l>
                              <l>And popular sway, by forcing Kings to give</l>
                              <l>More then was fit for Subjects to receive,</l>
                              <l>Ran to the same extreames; and one excesse,</l>
                              <l>Made both, by striving to be greater, lesse.</l>
                              <l>When a calme River rais'd with sudden raines,</l>
                              <l>Or Snowes dissolv'd, o're flowes th'adjoyning Plaines,</l>
                              <l>The Husbandmen<note type="gloss">Farmers.</note> with high-rais'd
                                    banks secure</l>
                              <l>They greedy hopes, and this he can endure.</l>
                              <l>But if with bayes, and Dammes they strive to force</l>
                              <l>His channell to a new, or narrow course;</l>
                              <l>No longer then within his banks he dwels,</l>
                              <l>First to a Torrent, then a Deluge swels:</l>
                              <l>Stronger, and fiercer by restraint he roares,</l>
                              <l>And knows no bound,but makes his power his shores.</l>
                        </div>

                        <div type="end">
                              <p>FINIS.</p>
                        </div>
                  </div>
            </body>
            <back>
                  <div type="colophon">
                        <p>This edition of John Denham's <title>Coopers Hill</title> was prepared
                              for SEL2218: <title>Research Project in English and History</title> by
                                    <ref
                                    target="https://www.ncl.ac.uk/elll/staff/profile/tiagosousa-garcia.html#background"
                                    >Dr. Tiago Sousa Garcia</ref>. It does not constitute a critical
                              edition but rather an enhanced transcript. The notes are partly
                              derived from Brendan O Hehir's <bibl><title>Expans'd hieroglyphicks: a
                                          critical edition of Sir John Denham's Coopers Hill</title>
                                          (<pubPlace>Berkeley</pubPlace>, <publisher>University of
                                          California Press</publisher>: <date>1969</date>)</bibl>.
                              The text was encoded in <ref target="https://tei-c.org/">TEI</ref>-XML
                              and transformed into HTML using an <ref
                                    target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XSLT">XSLT</ref>
                              transformation (ask Tiago if you want to know more). You can find the
                                    <ref
                                    target="https://github.com/tiagosousagarcia/Denham-Coopers-Hill-SDE/tree/SEL2218_Edition/TEI"
                                    >source TEI files here</ref> and the <ref
                                    target="https://github.com/tiagosousagarcia/Denham-Coopers-Hill-SDE/blob/SEL2218_Edition/Transformations/TEI_XHTML.xsl"
                                    >XSLT transformation here</ref>.</p>
                  </div>
            </back>
      </text>
</TEI>
